[SPEAKER_01]: So, a simple question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is pain a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is first?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want it, thus it's a problem, or it's a problem, thus you don't want it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is first?
[SPEAKER_01]: My... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is not wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is the pain a problem that's not wanted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you make it a problem because you don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop
[SPEAKER_01]: Resisting pain, as in stop trying to get rid of the pain, pain ceases to be a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, it gets too much pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is too much?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you get too much pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends what you mean by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you mean too much of painfulness of the pain, in which case, well, as long as you're still alive, it's not too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you mean, this is too much of a problem for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't have a problem with pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there cannot be too much of a pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha gave that example of highway robbers sawing your limbs off one by one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if the mind has ill will towards them, means it hasn't fulfilled the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because by fulfilling the dhamma, it's inconceivable to have ill-will towards pain or those who cause it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was not conceivable to begin with, but it was your ignorance of it that was conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, back to the same simple question, which is a reflection anybody can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is painful feeling a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I would prefer pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so why would I prefer pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why... why is it better then?
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize you won't find an objective answer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have an attitude of not wanting pain and you have an attitude of wanting pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your whole life is dictated by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at that attitude as to why is that attitude there, you won't find an answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's Kṛṭṣṛṛa's attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that... that's the only thing, the only... one and only reason for human suffering of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant by craving means suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of craving means absence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving is that attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this, I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if a person just starts reflecting, don't jump into answering right away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just wise pain, any pain, physical, emotional, any pain, any disagreeable feeling that I'm experiencing, why is it not wanted by default?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that my default attitude?
[SPEAKER_01]: And by putting yourself in such a question, without providing a rational answer, you're becoming aware of that problem, the problem of your attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes, yeah, sometimes maybe you have to keep that question for days, as a way of contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to keep repeating it, just don't answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep asking yourself, but look for an answer, but don't answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're looking, but you're not allowing yourself to formulate it in that rational, psychologizing manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you really want to become aware on that emotional level of your resistance to the unpleasant emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can give this answer or that answer, but emotionally, you'll still be resisting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you would still want to prolong it, if it's pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is absolutely no justifiable reason for not wanting pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if your attitude towards your feelings matters, you would feel only what you want to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, feelings would be obeying the attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that you're experiencing pain, which is not wanted, means you have absolutely no say in the domain of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of feeling is unaware of your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant feeling feels pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasant feeling feels displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral feeling feels neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't exist for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your attitude is a self-assumed parasite upon it, because of which you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the pain, the experience of pain, does not experience the dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience of pain, you resisting it, you experience the dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you get to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your sense of self, and the gratuitous assumption, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, pleasure, displeasure, and neutral remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were never a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In as much as any feeling is inevitable for as long as you're alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either pleasure, displeasure, or neither pleasure nor displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the attitude is... Gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's either you have attitude, or you have undone the attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe the type of attitude...
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the type of attitude is not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because...
[SPEAKER_01]: In pleasure, you will always be wanting more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: In pain, you will always want to try and get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a neutral feeling, you're always going to distract yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your attitudes are determined by the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving has set outcomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's optional is how you're going to go about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's already far down the line.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamental is the attitude of wanting, not wanting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamental is the attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamental is craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, craving for pleasure in more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for more pleasure in pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for absence of pain in pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for distraction, oblivion in either pleasant or unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that attitude can become apparent if you start questioning yourself in regard to the presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I feeling now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether something happened to you, somebody said something, you're upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I need to... Well, first, you have to stop projecting the blame, so to speak, and responsibility onto the world for your pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because as long as you still think that I'm suffering because such and such person said this and this, you have a lot of work to do, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you have many views to undo.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you take responsibility for how you're feeling and stop blaming the world, then you might be able to start discerning your attitude in regard to your own feeling as a primary and only, one and only source of your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, a person who is fully projected onto the world, being the reason for my pain, they can never see that, because they haven't taken responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, say, you've taken responsibility for you being affected by your feelings, so you stop trying to, you know, talk things out with somebody who upsets you, nothing, like, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's sort of done to, like, maintain social norms, that's fine, but you don't do it as a means of escape from your feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize that responsibility for you being affected by what's being felt, is on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the circumstances, not on the elements, not on other people, not of who said what, not of, oh, they didn't respect me enough, or they didn't do this, or they didn't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is you... you took for granted the attitude of trying to get rid of this unpleasure... unpleasurable feeling, and then, where you look, where would you go about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You... aha!
[SPEAKER_01]: He said this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's his fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: This happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't have enough luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's everyone else's fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if people are genuinely rude and mean to you, if you suffer on account of it, that's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said the wise monk, the one with the well-wisdom and right view, would endure harsh words, slander and all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you would endure elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you would endure heat, cold, hunger, insect bites, slanderous and abusive words.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you being upset on account of it, that's a new point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is pain a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to reveal the attitude, your attitude, that makes it a problem, that feeds the attitude, that makes it a problem, that feeds the attitude, vicious circle, in order to reveal it, you have to stop blaming pain for a problem, for the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, no,
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I have a problem with pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a more accurate question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because pain in itself isn't the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a problem in regard to the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the pain is not wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is the pain not wanted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I want it then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why would you want it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you have to either want or not want?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why can you just be equanimous in regard to either?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I don't want pain, but I do not not want pain either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any pain, big or small, far or near, past, future, any.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attitude in regard to any pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop trying to get rid of it, then the attitude towards pleasure becomes also apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop trying to entertain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop trying to make it stay longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop trying to get more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, automatically, by discerning the nature of your attitude towards pain, you also start discerning the nature of attitude towards pleasure, the gratuitous assumption of sensuality, sensual desire and pleasure you get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean you stop perceiving agreeable and disagreeable things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another thing is craving for more of it, and craving for that absence, and craving for your distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a nature of pain ceases to be a problem for a person, they have nothing else to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't matter where it comes from, from what sense, from what thought, from what experience, from what circumstance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is not resisted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is not feared.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is not wanted either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes people would go the other way and overly indulge pain as a mean of showing that, you know... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If pain has arisen, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a secondary thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if pain arises on account of your restraint and determination and willpower, you have no problem with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If pain arises on account of somebody abusing you,
[SPEAKER_01]: Offending you, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no problem with that either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't allow yourself to be abused.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you allow yourself to be abused when you give in to the attitude towards pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become abused.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, like, yeah, the circumstances are abusive, but you are not abused until you put the projection on the circumstances for that abuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you realize that abuse... that abuse is founded upon your attitude towards the experienced feeling at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that attitude is attitude of, I don't want this, you made yourself affected by that abuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I mean, so sexual abuse and sexual... Well, how can you be sexually abused?
[SPEAKER_01]: The body can be sexually abused, physically abused.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the kind of normal sexual relationship with people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means that people gratuitously take the ownership of the body to be theirs.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we all know how that ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sickness, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it was a mistake to take it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you better undo that mistake while you're alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you reflect.
[SPEAKER_01]: If this body were truly mine, in the same sense that I said, if the feelings were truly yours, your attitude would be the first and your feelings would be determined by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not your attitude would be determined by the corresponding feeling that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, oh, so my attitude is secondary to this, yet it's acting like it's some sort of commander-in-chief.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, me resisting pain, is my attitude towards the reason pain, which has a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I were to develop the attitude of, hold on, that's not a problem, and I stop gratuitously resisting it, you won't be able to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the body gets, somebody attacks you, beats you up physically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Through gratuitous assumption of the ownership of that body, that's how you become beaten up and abused.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter what type of assault and abuse it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, it can be done only to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only to the... literally to this bag of... bag of skin filled with lots of other organs and things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you thinking that you have a say,
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimate say, in what befalls that body, well, that was your ignorance from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you never get physically abused, you will be abused, your body will be abused, by aging, sickness and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the ultimate abuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: No amount of physical abuse, if it doesn't kill you, can amount for the the abuse of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is inevitable for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you realize that the attitude of abuse comes from you accepting the ownership of the body that has been abused, and you accept it through wanting pleasure through it, and you accept it through wanting to get rid of the pain through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it comes down again to the feelings that are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant feeling of abuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you don't even think twice before you start blaming, feeling what happened to the body and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you had enough mindfulness and self-reflection, you realize that, yeah, it's unfortunate, but that's the subject of elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: Form is being deformed by elements, by other bodies, other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just nature of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: By sickness, aging, death, whatever, accidents.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it was actually my mistake to assume that I had a say in that domain, to gratuitously entertain the attitude of saying no to this, or saying yes, I want more of this, whereby I have no say in arising of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I have a say in prolonging it, or not arising in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you have a say
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of the discrepancy, not because of the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is the discrepancy that your attitude creates in regard to the present feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the feeling is pleasurable, you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: when you want more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the discrepancy there is pleasant feeling and wanting more of it, as in not enough of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to stop wanting more of it, then you're only going to have a pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no discrepancy, no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consequently, you have the unpleasant feeling present, pain is present, and you don't want that presence at all, which means you're overdoing it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is some pain,
[SPEAKER_01]: But your attitude does not want any of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another discrepancy you created it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If all you had is your attitude towards pain, you would be in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, there is the actual pain there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's your attitude that contradicts it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, this pain must not be while the pain is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this pleasure must be greater while it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: This neutral feeling...
[SPEAKER_01]: This neutral feeling... What neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a neutral feeling, but you're not seeing any neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why when you're bored, you feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is...
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're bored, basically, you feel neither pleasure nor unpleasure, but that in itself, it's unpleasant for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to feel something, because the threshold of your discernment of feeling is pain and pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even see the neutral one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a slightly subtle discrepancy, but nevertheless, it's a discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably, you know it's a presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you stop contradicting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No contradiction, no discrepancy, no discrepancy, no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is a discrepancy created when your attitude clashes with the world, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And world can present itself only in three forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Agreeable, disagreeable and neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you deal on that level, you don't have to worry about anything else more particular than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how to deal with it on that level?
[SPEAKER_01]: To take responsibility for whatever is being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, this is felt by me because of my attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm making the feeling affect me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling of pleasure, feeling of pain, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody says something upsetting and the suffering, the pain arises, that's not... that pain is not in what's being said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in that person.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in any of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in your attitude in regard to the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to take responsibility for suffering, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to take responsibility for agreeable and disagreeable, but you have to take responsibility for wanting agreeable and not wanting disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean by taking responsibility?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means seeing that it's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no excuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm responsible for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when I suffer, I'm responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only through that attitude you can actually get a glimpse at least and maybe even, you know, go through with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can figure out how to not suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as your attitude doesn't take on suffering as your responsibility, and conflates suffering with disagreeable circumstances, with painful circumstances, you're not going to see the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you free yourself from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to stop blaming painful circumstances for your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is not the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is pain without suffering, but there cannot be suffering without pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you remove your attitude of denial and trying to get rid of the pain, you won't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you remove your attitude and indulgent in regard to the pleasure, you won't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't suffer on account of either pleasure or pain or neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you do that... Well, the more you... like, this attitude is maintained through not knowing it, through gratuitously assuming it at face value and acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's all you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't decide to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, now I will stop trying to get rid of the feeling of unpleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But through understanding your attitude towards it, that attitude is being gradually cancelled out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I feel pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind jumps to blame the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_01]: How many times has this happened?
[SPEAKER_01]: Many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: How many times will it happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I have a say in circumstances?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I then keep sort of, like, inflaming myself with this attitude of, yeah, this or this or that person?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It just feeds the fire further, while I kind of know already that that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's really like indignation and anger and that needs constant maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs constant action to make it valid.
[SPEAKER_01]: Constant blame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Find a scapegoat for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's his fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that false?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who's gonna pay for this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there are mistakes, and people do things that are unwise, and they're responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you suffer on account of it, that responsibility is solely yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say the body is sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sickness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a sickness, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but you have to kind of, you know, sort yourself out, take some medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's all fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be managing the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't want to be doing it out of a... out of trying to get rid of the suffering, because that inquires you identifying suffering with disagreeable circumstances of an ailing body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how do you know whether you're acting out of it or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I don't take the medicine?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I don't go and see the doctor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I going to get filled with anxiety and fear in regard to this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I going to suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: And we're going to experience mental anguish, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is yes, means you are still conflating suffering with circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just give up the medicines.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then you realize whether you give up the medicines or not, that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is you confusing your suffering with disagreeable feeling that has arisen on the level of an ailing body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are making it into your mental language, because of the gratuitous attitude of trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you can take a step further and reflect, okay, so this is the work that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to do that work, I need to stay alive, so I'll take the medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like, properly reflecting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you take the medicine as like a borrowing the time, so that you can uproot the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't take the medicine out of that blind... blind sort of just jump into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, and then I'll practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You got to look after your tools, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course, of course, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is a tool, on account of which you can understand the nature of the body, the nature of non-ownership, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that, you need it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why we say he wisely avoids a wild elephant, the one who practices dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wisely avoids a snake, a charcoal pit, a pack of dogs, because he would be foolish, before he has completed the work, to ignore the fact that this might kill him.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't, you know, you don't go around with an attitude of health is good in itself, as in the health is the greatest value.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're going to be sorely disappointed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, health is basically a tool.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, okay, my health is not perfect, but the tool is still good enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can also then realize that you're able to go quite far with the attitude that it's good enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is good enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it comes down to, well, as long as I'm still alive, and, you know, my senses are still there, it's still good enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're in pain and discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to go and seek out intense feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only changing my attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if somebody has that thought, where would that action intention be rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fear of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, I don't need to go out, because I just now revealed to myself that I'm trying to get rid of the suffering by thinking I'll go out and do this and this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you get rid of the suffering, where you recognize your attitude in regard to the disagreeable feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is always... well, there's a feeling always present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the work is always present.
[SPEAKER_01]: The work is always present in the sense of being mindful of the attitude towards the present feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in order to be mindful of the present feeling, you have to stop blaming the circumstances for the arising of that feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to feel it, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to allow it to be felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindful of the craving, the attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can't be mindful of the craving as I'm craving and craving and craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be mindful of the feeling and then discern the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, can I?
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: My attitude is always second to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no... it's inconceivable to be different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once that which you have been prioritized, which you have been prioritizing, is seen as second, it's not a priority anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that attitude is not a priority, that's how the attitude starts to fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through being mindful of the enduring feeling, you get to discern the nature of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why mindfulness is the basis of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like pain of restraint, saying no to yourself, saying no to sensual indulgence, saying no to laziness, saying no to ill-will, acting out of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: It produces pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is that discrepancy of I want to do this, but you say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, where is that discrepancy really rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it rooted in you want this and saying no to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it rooted in you want this, saying no to this, that's experienced disagreeably, that you don't want?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, circumstances arising, say, like a prospect of ill-will, but you restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that, you're experiencing this pain now, unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you're resisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, circumstances
[SPEAKER_01]: Even wanting to act out of it wasn't a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It became a problem when circumstances, they were unpleasant, you wanted to get rid of the displeasure through affecting the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you go and shout, beat people up, threaten them, so they never ever say that to you again.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you are not affected by the feeling of what's being said, how could you even conceive act of your will?
[SPEAKER_01]: And same as we spoke in many other talks, sensuality as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first, eh... the first relationship with sensual prospect of every mind that's universal is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sensuality is so intoxicating, because it's felt
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's
[SPEAKER_01]: Of of sensual indulgence presents itself, it's felt very painfully to not give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And automatically, you blame your attitude of not giving in for the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you realize, wait a minute, my attitude is a negative attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'm not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Negative attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Negative attitude means sensuality has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, go and eat all these cakes that you want now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not actually eating the cakes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're still not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your response is a negative response.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, not a bad response.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not a bad response in a negative, like, oh, it's bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it means it's basically not a positive action.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a... it's a call to a positive action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go and... go and get these cakes and eat them and enjoy the sense of taste you get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, all of that is still your thought and you are not eating it, you're not making any effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a negative experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's absence of these cakes that will provide me with these great pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of your attitude that always welcomes greater pleasure from the currently experienced feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the prospect of greater pleasure immediately is experienced as that great discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then people would give in, go and get all these cakes and overeat and whatnot, because they wanted to avoid the pain in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But can you really avoid, as in, can you really prevent the pain in the first place by doing that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or can you just covering it up and distract yourself from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize you can't avoid it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that by giving in value to the joy that comes out of taste, through eating all these cakes in this example, you gave in the value, you confirmed that you were affected by it in the first place, by that pain of not having that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as we said before, people think sensuality is unpleasant because they say no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through saying no to sensuality, you realize that the pain that you've been attributing to you saying no, as in not giving in to the positive action, the pain of it is basically in that positive action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to get rid of sensuality and pain of sensuality and dependence and pressure and burden and all of it, you just need to stick to saying no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the nature of it will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not doing anything now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thought of sensuality comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restraint is closer to the natural state you were before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the thought of sensuality that pressures you to go and do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pain arises on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the discrepancy that's being created.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were not doing anything before sensuality and you're not doing anything when you're restraining sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the constant there.
[SPEAKER_01]: What has changed is absence of sensuality before the pain and then presence of sensuality when the pain is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, wait a minute, it's the presence or absence of sensuality craving for that pleasure
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what creates the discrepancy of pain, of suffering, on account of sensuality, not my restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: My restraint is more like emulation of the proper behavior, of the proper action, of the action that doesn't give in to the pressure of sensuality or your will and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the restraint, self-composure, virtue has to come first, because it starts emulating things rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know it yet,
[SPEAKER_01]: But on that ground, you can get to know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, inevitably, pain is going to be felt when you say no to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you accept it, then you can say, basically, to the pain and to yourself, that that pain belongs to this sensuality, not to the restraint of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I said restraint is that negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's no action there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's abstaining from action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've been abstaining from sensual action when there was no sensuality pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, sensuality is pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're practicing restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you're on the same level of abstaining from that action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's different?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's absence or presence of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it becomes even more apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one thing for sure, you'll never find peace
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, ultimate freedom, in the sense of not being pressured by circumstances, if you keep engaging with sensuality, with gratuitous cravings of pleasure through your senses, with gratuitous expressions of your ill-will through your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether sensuality touches you, whether ill-will touches you, whether boredom touches you, what do they all have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a disagreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having an attitude of wanting to get rid of disagreeable means what?
[SPEAKER_01]: In sensuality, how do you get rid of disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying yes to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In ill-will, how do you get rid of the disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: By affecting the person or whatever circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying yes to it, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In boredom, how do you get rid of disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying yes to it and finding things to distract yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you have a positive attitude that result in positive actions of indulgence, ill-will, distraction, greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not metaphysical things, the things that your attitudes are based on, your actions are based on, because of your attitude in regard to how you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, that's what the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it's felt, counts as suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, feeling of agreeable, pressures you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling of disagreeable, pressures you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling of neutral, pressures you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, that pressure is not in the feeling or on the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pressure is in your ignorance of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are pressured in regard to pleasure, because you haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are pressured in regard to this pleasure, because you haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what Guruji said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the neutral feeling is not understood, it's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the neutral feeling is understood, there is no pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want sensuality in order to be free from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have ill will and anger in order to be free from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have distraction, boredom, indolence, laziness in order to be free from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting to be free from pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you stop equating that with trying to get rid of this pain, then you can actually learn how to free yourself from pain, from being affected by the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will truly be free from pain, not when pain stops arising, but when your attitude towards pain changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's again just to also add to what you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to go out seeking out suffering and pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just say no to your desires, and the pain is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to go and risk your life and feel threatened and get, you know, that existential dread going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just start saying no to your daily sense desires, and you'll see how quickly the pain will come knocking on your door.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the attitude is developed towards pain is not the problem, it's my attitude towards pain that's problem, then no amount of pain can prevail over the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it would have meant for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The disagreeable feelings cannot overwhelm his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is the one who overwhelms.
[SPEAKER_01]: His mind overwhelms the disagreeable feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or he is the one who overwhelms his mind in regard to disagreeable feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not just that he needs to do that as like some sort of, you know, a determination, sort of willpower practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through understanding, that's just a natural state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: When disagreeable arises, it has arisen overwhelmed by the mind that has understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, understanding overwhelms the disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of understanding automatically is higher than disagreeable, or agreeable, or neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, none of those feelings can overwhelm it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not on the level of just I'm doing this, it's on the level of this, this thing, this pain that's there, there is the understanding of that pain that's there, simultaneously with that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand what's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that understanding depends on what's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But whenever that thing is there, it has been understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you theorized about it and rationalized about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what's been understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of agreeable feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of disagreeable feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's just another way of saying there is no more attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no more assumed, almost entitled attitude in regard to pleasure, pain, or neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, pleasure feels pleasantly, displeasure feels unpleasantly, and neutral feelings feel neutrally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no suffering in regard to any.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we started by saying, why is pain a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why am I making a problem out of pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I making a problem out of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, I'm not making a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where you are?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are pressured by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If pleasure is truly not a problem, you wouldn't suffer on account of not getting enough of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whichever shape or form pleasure would arise,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be self-sufficient to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there would be no craving for more sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a thought of, as we said, of going and eating up all the nice sweet cakes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That thought is agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nice, nice cakes, nice, nice taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, that's sufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would now that thought pressure you to go and make all these actions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Finding cake, getting cake, eating cake, consuming cake, all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you were affected by that pressure on the level of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were affected, the only means of you dealing with being pressured and experiencing disagreeable, is seeking out what it sort of points at.
[SPEAKER_01]: The cake at the mouth and eating, shoving cake in your mouth, all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all that's secondary to the thought of that pleasure of the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were indifferent to the pleasure of the taste on the level of the thought, committing actions on account of it becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean that you don't recognize this is a tasty cake and this is not a tasty food.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that experience can then
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only reason you'll be going there and doing this and eating, because the context of
[SPEAKER_01]: The thought of consuming a tasty food is still there, giving the meaning to all of your individual actions of getting there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, once you go and eat the cake, you never can fulfill that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because thought is a thought, and taste is a taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely different sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you were assuming this identity of the whole projection, the whole action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thought of a pleasant taste, consumption of the pleasant taste, it's identified.
[SPEAKER_01]: But deep down, it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's obvious to everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody will say, people who never read Buddhism practically, yeah, you know, like, you can't really satisfy your desires, can't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's nothing to satisfy.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was a pleasure, initial pleasure on the level of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's your attitude that automatically wants more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you think more about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That wants more pleasure, so you go and do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, it's attitude of wanting more pleasure in regard to the thought of pleasure, that's the discrepancy that's being created there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that attitude is why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That attitude is why you assume the whole world of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you undo the attitude of automatically wanting pleasure and automatically not wanting pain, then you have an agreeable thought of some nice, very, like, tasty food, or agreeable thought of some beautiful music, or agreeable thought of beautiful sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just beautiful things that you thought about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that agreeability of them, stays with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no attitude of you, I want more of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, in the thought, there will be only the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sight, there will be only the sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sound, you hear something pleasant, that pleasure is confined to that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't interfere with it, through your attitude of wanting more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't interfere with it through an attitude of trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the sin, there'll just be the sin, in the hurt, there'll just be the hurt, the bahir-sutta, the famous bahir-sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you got so absorbed in the sin that there's only the sin.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's because in the sin, there can only be the sin.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have the something else in the sin.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's there, it's sin.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have the hurt in the sin, or the thought in the sin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inasmuch you can't have the scene in the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I'm saying here.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sensuality is on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even for the Tāgata, the beautiful things remain in the world, but it's the desire and lust, his thought, and desire and lust that's been perpetuated through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what he has uprooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a thought of sensual pleasure is agreeable on the level of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize that is... that is the extent of its gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: That... that initial agreeability.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's as much as you can get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you remove the attitude towards wanting more of it, you remove any basis for spreading of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no spreading of sensuality, sensuality will cease, because it requires maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Avijja requires maintenance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance requires maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is a thought of, I've been offended, he said something rude to me, or, oh, these people might come and kill me.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not trying to get rid of the displeasure of that thought,
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be affected by anything that happens through that port.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly won't be able to engage with anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you wouldn't be able to kill somebody even in self-defense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to defend.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is pain not wanted and why is pleasure wanted?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about getting rid of the pleasure or having more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about getting rid of the pain, making it never appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about not wanting one and not trying to get rid of the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can't say... You have a say, you have a thought, as we said, of eating some tasty food.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you're full-on chugging food down your throat, just swallowing it, and saying to yourself, but see, I don't want it on the level of my thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I would have said it's impossible to engage physically with sensuality without having sensual perceptions on the level of thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the sensory strain, the physical restraint, needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's based on that wrong discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through engaging with it, you're affirming the discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're affirming the discrepancy, you're affirming suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you get rid of suffering when you're affirming it through your own very actions?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're building up on suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take suffering as your foundation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means any of your efforts cannot really pertain to suffering, to undoing of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But covering, trying to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But trying to get rid of it is perpetuation of the attitude that creates the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your attitude creates the problem and problem perpetuates it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once created.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... but there is no first point where that problem wasn't... was created and wasn't before.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no first point to avidya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can just think about pain, as we started.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you remove the attitude of not wanting pain, you're automatically dealing with sensuality, with pleasure, and with pain, and with ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would give in to sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's unpleasant to not do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the way of getting rid of that displeasure is by doing so.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what if you're not affected by that displeasure in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you realize, oh, there's nothing for me to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing for me to get engaged with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentionality is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you've given in to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want to look as to why did you have to give in to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what... like what we spoke before, like the willpower and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you should use willpower.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like saying no to everything and overcoming and making it like, you know, prevailing over every single thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just find things on account of which you suffer, which is your attitude in regard to pleasure, your attitude in regard to pain, your attitude in regard to neither pleasure nor pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, prevail there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to worry about anything else then, because whatever you do won't be unwholesome, because it's only rooted in trying to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not rooted in the discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's our own ignorance, and our own actions rooted in it, that are perpetuating it, that is obscuring the nature of things as they actually are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remove your discrepant attitude, or attitude that results in discrepancy, that creates it, that generates it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you see the way things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the seen, there's just the seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: There never was anything more.
[SPEAKER_01]: There couldn't have been anything more.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the felt, there was just the felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the perceived, there was the perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the intended, there was the intended.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the world, there was just the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you can truly learn from your pain, whatever that pain is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through, like, psychologizing and developing some nice, pleasing theories, hence your learning, inverted commas.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: With presence of pain, you automatically, simultaneously, must have presence of that gratuitous attitude, unless you're fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through presence of disagreeable, you have a basis for undoing your attitude towards the disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, yeah, pain is a great teacher, if done rightly, if you know how to look at it, if you have a right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you know where to look, then all you have to do is practice composure, self-control, restraint, because all these things will be revealing the nature of feelings that are experienced unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be revealing the displeasure of sensuality, the displeasure of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll be revealing it, not creating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once you reveal the
[SPEAKER_01]: The displeasure that was making you have the attitude towards getting rid of the displeasure, you start to undo the attitude automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That work can be in front of you, always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is always, because it's always something felt, which means there's always attitude in regard to whatever's being felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You say that's the only work that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the work on the most fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you fix things on the most fundamental level, everything else built on top of it will be fixed equally.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you purify the stream at its very origin, top of the mountain, eventually, even the rivers and seas that are being filled by that stream will be purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can be battling and trying to purify the rivers down there, down the mountain, while there is still the source of pollution remains,
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how, you know, when the Buddha said he purifies his mind from unwholesome thoughts, from thoughts of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly how it's done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by chasing every individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I was thinking this.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the nature of this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was it rooted in trying to get rid of the pain caused by sensual pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Prospect of sensual pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was it rooted in trying to get rid of the pain caused by something disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was it trying to get rid of the pain caused by something agreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was it trying to get rid of the pain caused by neutral?
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, it's going to be either sensuality, ill-will or delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't entertain it on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how he purifies his behavior in every other regard.